this problem requires
us to obtain two integers from the user
and print the results of dividing the
first by the second
we must ensure that the second number is
not zero
and we also need to validate both
numbers using
a method that has been given to us
called valid number
this method will return a boolean and
it's just a simplified way to verify
whether the user input was valid
there are edge cases for which this
valid number method would not work
but it's sufficient for this exercise
you can see on line two that we're using
comparison so we know that this method
will return either true or false
if it returns true we'll assume the
number is valid
and if it returns false we'll assume
that it is invalid
we've also been given some example code
to see what
the prompts of our program should look
like in this problem we're not
accepting floats as input and the
division that we're doing is going to be
integer division
the first thing that we want to do is
prompt the user to
enter the numerator we'll call put s
and tell them to please enter the
numerator
[Music]
and we can store that input in a local
variable numerator
[Music]
and remember that we'll use chomp to
remove the newline character from the
end of the user input
we need to pass numerator to our valid
number method as an
argument
and to see this working let's output the
return value of this
[Music]
and run our code a few times
first i'll enter a valid number let's
use
4 and you can see that the valid number
method returned
true let's see what happens if i enter
a letter instead
[Music]
and the method we use to validate the
number returned false
[Music]
lastly let's test if we input a float
again our valid number method returns
false
[Music]
now we don't want to actually output the
return value of valid number what we're
using that for
is input validation
we'll use a simple loop
[Music]
and only break out of this loop if the
user input is valid
so we'll add the reserve word break on
line eight and
a condition will break if the numerator
is a valid number
so if our method call to valid number
returns true
we'll break out of the loop otherwise
we'll continue to loop
and prompt the user to enter the
numerator
now we want to tell the user if their
input was invalid
so perhaps they didn't realize that only
integers were allowed and they tried to
enter a float
our error message directs the user to
only enter an integer
[Music]
running our code again you can see if i
enter a
g which is an invalid input
i see the appropriate error message and
i'm prompted again
this time when i enter 4 which is valid
input
i have no error message and we've broken
out of the loop
now the numerator is not the only user
input that we need here
we also need the user to enter a
denominator
and we need to make sure that the
denominator is not zero
so we'll use a similar loop structure
but we need to change our code up a
little bit
so we'll prompt the user to enter the
denominator
[Music]
and we'll store it in a local variable
called denominator
on line 17 we need to pass denominator
to the valid number method
and we still want to display the same
error message we see on line
18 if somebody enters anything that's
not an integer
for the denominator
running our code again i'll enter a
valid numerator
and an invalid denominator
you can see that the error message is
still displayed appropriately
and when i enter a valid denominator
[Music]
we break out of the loop so that's okay
but what happens if i run the program
again and i enter
0 for the denominator
[Music]
our program accepts it and breaks out of
the loop
but we can't allow 0 for the denominator
so let's add an if statement and compare
denominator to
[Music]
zero we'll tell the user specifically
that a denominator of 0 is not allowed
[Music]
now if this code looks correct to you
rethink what our user input is
recall that we've never converted the
user input into an integer
so we should be comparing our
denominator
to a string representation of 0.
[Music]
now when i enter a denominator of zero i
get a specific error message
telling me that i did not enter the
correct value
however we still broke out of our loop
so we need to take a closer look at that
i should have been prompted again to
enter a new denominator after the error
message was issued
[Music]
you can see that after line 18 was
executed and the error message was
displayed
our code continued down through the loop
and executed line
21. now our valid number method will
return true for zero
so we only want to execute the code
that's currently on line 21
if denominator is not equal to zero
what we can do is actually expand our if
statement
[Music]
we can put this code on lines 21 and 22
into an else branch of this if statement
and then it will only be executed if
line
17 does not evaluate as true
[Music]
in an if-else statement only one of
these two branches will be executed
so if our condition on line 17 evaluates
as true
then line 18 will be executed and we'll
go back to the beginning of this loop
otherwise if the denominator is not
equal to 0
then lines 20 and 21 our else branch
will be executed
and we'll be given the option to break
out of the loop if the denominator is a
valid number
so let's run our code now
[Music]
i'll enter a valid numerator and this
time when i enter 0 as the denominator
not only will i see the error message
displayed but i'll be prompted again to
enter
a valid denominator
and when i do we break out of the loop
so at this point we're successfully
validating both pieces
of information that we're soliciting
from the user
[Music]
the last step here is to actually
perform the integer division and display
it to the user
[Music]
let's initialize a local variable result
and recall that we did not convert
numerator and denominator to integers
earlier in our code
so we'll need to do that now
[Music]
and we'll do that by calling the
string2i method
for now let's output our result
[Music]
i'll enter two valid integers
we're dividing four by two
and you'll see that an exception was
raised
on line 25 ruby sees an undefined local
variable or method numerator
going back to our code line 25
is when we try to access numerator and
denominator
in the outer scope however numerator and
denominator were both initialized
in the inner scope of a block so it's
not possible for us to access them in
this outer scope on line 25.
in order to solve this issue we can
initialize these variables
in the outer scope
and because we don't solicit the input
from the user until later
we'll set them equal to nil for now and
now
numerator on line 8 is not a new
variable being initialized
it's an existing variable that was
initialized in the outer scope
being reassigned
and we can do the same for denominator
now we can expect that our code will run
without error
and the result of our integer division
is 2.
[Music]
we want to display this a little bit
more nicely to the user
so we'll create a nice message that
displays the numerator the denominator
and the result
now we could display this with either
string concatenation or string
interpolation
let's use interpolation
[Music]
now we can display a nice message to the
user
[Music]
and it displays 4 divided by 2 is 2.
you